A Guide to the Elsa Leviseur Architectural Collection, 1950-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Elsa Leviseur Architectural Collection, 1950-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-007
13.2 cu. ft.
Born 1932. Practiced architecture and landscape architecture in South Africa, England, and California. Projects include designs for the Hollywood Bowl and the Los Angeles Philharmonic Association in California. Papers consist of files, photographs, specifications, and architectural drawings of designs done mostly in the 1980s.
Leviseur, Elsa
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The records were donated in January 1990 by Elsa Leviseur to the International Archive of Women in Architecture housed in the Special Collections Department of the University Libraries at Virginia Tech.
Biographical/Historical note
Elsa Leviseur is an architect of Los Angeles, California, born in South Africa in 1932. She earned a B. Arch. at the University of Cape Town School of Architecture in 1954 and a M. A. in Architecture and Urban Planning from the University of California at Los Angeles Graduate School of Architecture and Urban Planning in 1980. She has been principal of Leviseur Architects in Santa Monica, California, since 1983. She was Principal of Architerra in Los Angeles from 1986 to 1989 and Project Manager of The Tanzmann Associates from 1980 to 1983. She worked in other architects offices and in private practive in England from 1960 to 1969 and in South Africa from 1954 to 1959.
Leviseur taught at Manchester Polytechnic in England in the early 1990s, and at the University of California, Los Angeles from 1984 to 1989. She has been a member of the Association for Women in Architecture since 1974 (she served as President in 1978), and was a founding member of Designers and Planners for Social Responsibility and member since 1984.
Scope and Content
The materials in the collection consist of architectural drawings, photographs, specifications, correspondence, news clippings, scrapbooks, and other materials.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series: I. Personal Papers; II. Professional Papers; and III. Project Records.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Architectural drawing--20th century.
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Local Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA).
Contents List
- Personal Papers.
  - B.A. Thesis, University of Cape Town--Photonegatives of Art Training Center, 1953. (Box-folder 1|2)
  - Curriculum Vitae. (Box-folder 18|16)
  - Landscape Sketches, n.d. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 6)
  - Master's Thesis--An Interpretive Ferry Service for the Santa Monica Mountains Recreation Area, 1980. (Box-folder 1|14, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 6)
  - Peter--Racing Car Design--Photographs, 1954. (Box-folder 1|3)
  - Photographs, Photo Plates, and Fixed Line Siver Halide. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 6, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 10)
  - Season's Greetings-Salutation-Fixed Line Silver Halide, n.d. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 6)
- Professional Papers, 1980-1985
  - Association for Women in Architecture Conference (Scripps College, Claremont, California)--Women Up Front: Architectural Options, 1982. (Box-folder 1|19, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 6)
  - Chronology of Year's Transmittals and Correspondence, 1985. (Box-folder 13|3)
  - Roosevelt Island Competition, Fixed Line Zinc Halide, 1975/ (Box-folder 1|13)
  - Santa Monica Multi-family Housing Rehabilitation (Santa Monica, California)--Description of firm qualifications for project, 1984. (Box-folder 13|2)
  - Stationary for Leviseur Architects, circa 1980s. (Box-folder 13|1, Box-folder 13|3, Box-folder 1|15)
  - Women in Environmental Design-Program Announcement, n.d. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 6)
  - Writings by and about Elsa Leviseur, 1984. (Box-folder 13|1)
- Project Records.
  Scope and Content
  The following is a list of architectural projects carried out by Elsa Leviseur and/or her firm Leviseur Architects.
  Arrangement
  The Project Index is a way to organize the various formats of architectural records from the same project. The index is arranged alphabetically by project and contains information, where available, about the location, date, project type, architect, collaborators, photographers, and formats for each project in the collection.
  Project Index
  A summary of the Project Index is listed below:
  Project/Client Name (location, date, project type, architect) Collaborator (role), Photographer [Format - Ms=Manuscripts, Dr=Drawings, Ph=Photographs, Sl=Slides, PB=Presentation Boards, Sm=Specifications Manual]
  - Summary of Project Index.
    - List of Projects, 1956-1985. (Box-folder 1|4)
    - Anstey Addition (Westerham, Kent, Great Britain, 1967, residential) [Dr, Ph]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4, Box-folder 1|7)
    - Anstey Residence (Dale Pembs, Wales, 1967-1968, residential) [Dr, Ph, Ms]. (Box-folder 1|8, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder4)
    - Anstey Vacation Cottage (Dales, Wales, 1969, residential) [Dr, Ph]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4, Box-folder 1|9)
    - Borun Addition (Los Angeles, CA, 1977, residential) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 3)
    - Camps Bay Residence ( Cape Town, South Africa, 1950, Residential ) [Ph]. (Box-folder 1|1)
    - Castro Crest Trailhead ( Santa Monica Mountains, California, 1986, Landscape ) [Dr,Ph,Ms,Sm]. (Box-folder 18|1-3, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 7, Box-folder 18|8)
    - Center Landscaping ( Unknown, Unknown, 1984, Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Chambers Addition ( Sherman Oaks, California, 1980, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Cherry Residence ( Santa Monica, California, 1976, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5)
    - Delaney Addition ( Los Angeles, California, 1977, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 3)
    - Dembeck/Warshaw Landscaping ( Los Angeles, California, 1984, Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2|Drawer 4|Folder 4)
    - Dewey Residence ( Unknown, Unknown, 1988, Residentail ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 8)
    - Drabkin Addition ( Brentwood, California, 1976, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 1)
    - Edna Erspamer Duplex ( Santa Monica, California, 1985, Residential ) [Dr,Ms,Sl,Sm]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 8, Box-folder 13|8-10)
    - Fitzerald Duplex ( Manhattan Beach, California, 1984, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5)
    - Fitzerald Duplex Addidtion ( Manhattan Beach, California, 1984, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5)
    - Fitzgerald Residence ( Manhattan Beach, California, 1984, Residential ) [Dr,Ms,Sm]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5, Box-folder 13|5)
    - Fleischer Landscape ( Los Angeles, California, 1987, Landscape ) [Ms]. (Box-folder 18|14)
    - Fleischmann Addition ( Brentwood, California, 1975, Residential ) [Dr,Ph]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 1, Box-folder 1|10)
    - Feuer Landscaping ( Malibu, California, 1985, Landscape ) [Ms]. (Box-folder 13|4)
    - Gould Residence-Phase 1 and Phase 2 ( Pacific Palisades, California, 1984-1989, Residential ) [Dr,Ms.Sm]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 10, Box 16, Box 15|1-13, Box 14)
    - Hart Residence ( Topanga, California, 1984-1988, Residential ) [Ph,Ms,Sm]. (Box-folder 16|1-11, Box-folder 15|14-19)
    - Henick Landscape ( Santa Monica, California, 1988, Landscape ) [Dr, Ph]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 7, Box-folder 18|15)
    - Hershey Residence ( Pacific Palisades, California, 1986, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 7)
    - Hinerfeld Residence ( Los Angeles, California, 1986, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5)
    - Hollywood Bowl ( Los Angeles, California, 1982-1988, Commercial ) [Ms]. (Box 19, Box 2)
    - Hollywood Bowl-Display/Sales Area ( Los Angeles, California, 1983-1984, Commercial ) [Dr,Ms,Sm]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 8, Box 7)
    - Hollywood Bowl-Marquee ( Los Angeles, California, 1983-1984, Commercial ) [Dr,Ms,Sm]. (Box-folder 9|17-21)
    - Hollywood Bowl-Museum ( Los Angeles, California, 1982-1985, Graphic Design ) [Dr,Ph,PB,Ms,SM]. (Oversize 2|5|6, Box-folder 3|10, Box-folder 6|8)
    - Hollywood Bowl-Restaurant ( Los Angeles, California, 1983-1984, Commercial ) [Dr,Ms]. (Box 10)
    - Hollywood Bowl- Season Ticket Office ( Los Angeles, California, 1983-1984, Commercial ) [Dr,Ph,Ms,Sm]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 7, Box 8-9, Box-folder 10|11, Box 3-6)
    - Hollywood Bowl-Studio Club ( Los Angeles, California; 1980; Commercial ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Horatio West Court Planting ( Santa Monica, California, n.d., Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Jager Addition ( Unknown, Unknown, n.d., Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 3)
    - Kelly, Tom, Photo Studio Addition ( West, Hollywood, California, 1985, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 8)
    - Knight Landscape Addition ( Brentwood, California, 1973, Residential ) [Dr,Ph]. (Box-folder 1|11, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5)
    - Long Addition ( Mandeville Canyon California, 1978, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Mayer Landscaping ( Sherman Oaks, California, 1986-1987, Landscape ) [Dr,Ms,Sl]. (Box-folder 17|13-15, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5)
    - Mendelsohn Residence ( Westwood, California, 1975, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 2)
    - Nelson Swimming Pool ( Le Mesa, California, 1978, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Neumann Addition ( Santa Monica, California, 1974, Residential ) [Dr, Ph]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 3)
    - New House ( Cape Town, South Africa, 1958, Residential ) [Ph]. (Box-folder 1|6)
    - Office Layout II for Los Angeles Philharmonic Association ( Los Angeles, California, 1985, Commercial ) [Dr,Ms,Sm]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 7, Box-folder 13|6-7)
    - O'Neil Remodel ( Los Angeles, California, 1970, Residential ) [Dr,Ph]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 10)
    - Ramirez Residence ( Los Angeles, California, 1985, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 8)
    - Robie Landscape ( Mandeville Canyon, California, 1989, Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 8)
    - Rose Landscaping ( Unknown, Unknown, 1988, Landscape ) [Dr,]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 5)
    - Sheinkopf Landscaping ( Palm Springs, California, 1978, Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Silverman Landscape ( Pacific Palisades, California, 1982, Landscape ) [Dr,Ms]. (Box-folder 1|17-18, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)
    - Southern California Counseling Center ( Los Angeles, California, 1981, Commercial ) [Ms,Sm]. (Box-folder 1|16)
    - Stiehm Addition ( Santa Monica, California, 1975, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 2)
    - Steinberg Landscaping ( Beverly Hills, California, 1972, Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 3)
    - Tamboers Koof Addition ( Cape Town, South Africa, 1958, Residential ) [Ph]. (Box-folder 1|5)
    - Teffeteller Addition ( Los Angeles, California, 1975-1976, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 2)
    - University of California at Davis-Arboretum Competition ( Davis, California, 1988, Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 9)
    - Weisenfeld Addition ( Brentwood, California, 1973, Residential ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 3)
    - Williams Residence ( Brookings, Oregon, 1986, Residential ) [Dr,Ph,Ms,Sm]. (Box-folder 18|4-18, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 9, Box-folder 17|1-12, Box-folder 16|12-20)
    - Wilshire Boulevard ( Santa Monica, California, 1983-1984, Public Works ) [Dr,Ph,PB,Ms]. (Box 11-12, Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 5/Folder 6)
    - Yorkshire Landscaping ( Beverly Hills, California, 1980, Landscape ) [Dr]. (Oversize Map-case 2/Drawer 4/Folder 4)